A Guide to the Walthall family papers, 1909-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Walthall family papers, 1909-1999
The Library of Virginia
50070
.225 cu. ft. and 1 box
Walthall family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 23 August 2011, from Crown Collectibles, Chesterfield, Virginia.
Biographical Information
William Warren Walthall (6 October 1891-12 April 1973) and Alice Ramos (November 1895-25 February 1964) were married 18 June 1917 in Richmond, Virginia. W. W. Walthall worked for the First and Merchants Bank and for the Office of the Treasurer for Virginia. Alice Walthall was active in charitable and educational organizations. They had three children, including James Barrett Walthall (17 June 1926-3 October 2005). James B. Walthall was active in the Democratic Party, serving on the City Democratic Committee. He was the Deputy City Treasurer for Richmond, and served on the Richmond Electoral Board. Walthall also served as Doorkeeper for the Virginia House of Delegates. He served on the boards of the Library of Virginia, the Virginia Historical Society, and other organizations. All three Walthalls are buried in Riverview Cemetery in Richmond.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1909-1999, of the Walthall family of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of accounts, certificates clippings, correspondence, envelopes, invitations, journals, membership lists, minutes, newsletters, pamphlets, passes, postcards, programs, purchase orders, receipts, reports, song sheets, tickets, and other papers concerning the family's involvement in politics, the Richmond Community Fund, the Jeb Stuart PTA, and the YMCA.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Politics, 1931-1999.
Series II: Richmond Community Fund, 1936-1940.
Series III: PTA, 1935-1939.
Series IV: YMCA, 1909-1912, 1948.
Contents List
- Series I: Politics, 1931-1999., Extent: 6 folders. (Folder 1-6)
  correspondence, envelopes, invitations, membership lists, newsletters, passes, post cards, programs, purchase orders, receipts, tickets, concerning the Walthall family's political activities, specifically James B. Walthall's. Subjects include the Richmond City Democratic Committee, the 1985 and 1989 Virginia Democratic party and state elections, the 1988 state Democratic presidential primary, gubernatorial inaugurations and addresses, abortion, sale of surplused chairs, and some personal papers regarding floor cleaning, electric power, and gas.
  - Richmond City Democratic Committee, 1986-1988. (Folder 1)
  - The Capital Democrat, 1987-1989. (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1999. (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1931-1999. (Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1985. (Folder 5)
  - Tickets and passes, 1985, 1989, 1999. (Folder 6)
- Series II: Richmond Community Fund, 1936-1940., Extent: 4 folders. (Folder 7-10)
  Series II: Richmond Community Fund, 1936-1940, contains papers relating to Mrs. W. W. Walthall's work for the Richmond Community Fund. Papers contain accounts, correspondence, minutes, newsletters, pamphlets, post cards, and song sheets detailing the Fund's solicitation campaigns and work with businesses and organizations like the Richmond Rubber Company, the Girl Scouts of Richmond, and the Northside Neighborhood Council.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1940. (Folder 7)
  - Solicitation campaign, 1939-1940. (Folder 8)
  - The Fund Campaigner, 1939. (Folder 9)
  - Papers, 1936-1940, no date. (Folder 10)
- Series III: PTA, 1935-1939., Extent: 6 folders. (Folder 11-16)
  Series III: PTA, 1935-1939, contains constitution and bylaws, correspondence, journals, newsletters, notices, receipts, reports, song sheets, and other papers relating to parent-teacher organizations and education in general. Includes papers on the Jeb Stuart School PTA, the National Congress of Parents and Teachers, and the Cooperative Education Association.
  - Jeb Stuart School PTA, 1935-1939. (Folder 11)
  - National Conference of Parents and Teachers, 1935-1938. (Folder 12)
  - Parent-Teacher News, 1937-1938. (Folder 13)
  - Cooperative Education Association, 1936. (Folder 14)
  - General education. (Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous papers. (Folder 16)
- Series IV: YMCA, 1909-1912, 1948, no date., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 17)
  Series IV: YMCA papers, 1909-1912, 1948, and no date, contains membership cards for the YMCA (1909-1910, 1912) and the YWCA (1948), and directions, no date, for the new YMCA building.
  - Papers, 1909-1912, 1948, no date. (Folder 17)